[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
what about the complexity of of the
black hole if it's going to model
completely this Collision what about
what about the complexity of it yeah in
other words it's not a stable black hole
it must be something Chang
shape and things like that yeah yeah um
that's
right here's the
picture you have a Fifth
Dimension and think of the Fifth
Dimension as existing between a floor
and a
ceiling ceiling
floor um there's a gravitational field
that pulls everything down to the floor
there are particles or strings or
whatever they
are which can live in this
five-dimensional world let's think of
them as little
strings and uh they tend to fall fall to
the bottom here when they fall to the
bottom they're hadrons they're protons
neutrons mesons and so forth if they get
stuck up at the top and they can't stick
to the ceiling
they can stick to the ceiling if they're
stuck up at the top they are gravitons
photons more Elementary
particles uh not the not the not hadrons
hadrons are big fat composite
objects
um when you Collide two hadrons that's
like colliding two particles that are on
the
floor the collide they make a big splash
of energy and the big splash of
energy is apparently nicely described
well described by saying that a black
hole forms a black hole is just a big
puddle of energy a big puddle of
energy um a
lump a lump with an edge The Edge is the
Horizon and like all black holes they
have temperature they have entropy they
have all the thermodynamic prop
properties of black holes and this
object is a kind of black hole that's
sitting down on the floor it's not the
kind of black holes
four-dimensional black holes black holes
that we think of as astronomical black
holes or the kind of black holes that we
would make by scattering particles and
enormous energies above the plunk scale
those kind of black holes also have
Horizons they're very similar except
they
are Dr droplets hanging from the ceiling
actually they hang this
way hanging from the ceiling attached to
the ceiling and uh they are stuck to the
ceiling ceiling is a sticky
ceiling but otherwise they're the same
kind of thing they're the same kind of
thing in five Dimensions they correspond
to black holes they correspond to
Horizons and they correspond to all the
things that uh that uh Steven Hawking
and others have studied over the years
now now if an enormously high energy
Collision happens an enormous lump of
energy remember what happens to
particles which are very high energy
they get collapsed like thin pancakes by
Lorent
contraction so what happens is two
pancakes they're moving in this
direction and this direction they're
thin they're like
pancakes so they I don't know how to
draw it exactly uh whatever they are
they're they're thin in this direction
and they come in and they Collide they
collide with an enormous amount of
energy and they make a great big puddle
of energy like that but that puddle of
energy is more or less like a lump of
viscous fluid and not so viscous any
rather unv viscous a lump of fluid
that's been deposited in this
gravitational field and the
gravitational P field pulls it down and
spreads it out and spreads it out
until it comes to some equilibrium like
a puddle on the
ground and it would stay that way except
for one thing and the one thing is
hawking radiation Hawking radiation
starts causing radiation to come out off
this thing and what is that radiation
that radiation is the ordinary particles
that we see protons
neutrons mesons and so forth uh that we
see coming out of this thing remember
when he uh when he showed us some of the
pictures of the events there was this
7,000 particles coming out of a little
dot here those 7,000 particles
are in this picture they're essentially
the Hawking radiation that's boiled off
the outer parts of this black hole
here um as I said whether you should
really think of it as a Fifth Dimension
and real honest to goodness black hole
sitting on the floor of The Fifth
Dimension here or whether you should
just think of it as a mathematical
analogy at this point I would say is up
to
you uh I think in time we will
understand better the connection between
these ideas and uh real
gravity my own guess is they will be
connected in a deep way and uh that uh
that we will learn to understand this
picture as part of a bigger
thing part of is will it be String
Theory will it be quantum gravity will
it be uh uh something that we haven't
seen yet but yeah I think the Fifth
Dimension is quite
real uh what does it mean to be real it
means it fits together with the other
dimensions in a mathematical structure
that
um uh I don't know that uh that makes
the laws of physics look
simple dividing this into real space and
a fictitious space and treating the
fictitious space completely different
seems to make the equations more
complicated than if you think of uh if
you really literally think of this as a
Fifth Dimension but this
five-dimensional structure here really
is nothing but Quantum
chromodynamics qcd the theory of qu and
gluons so uh as I say at the moment it's
kind of up to you whether you want to
think of it as having any reality or
whether you just want to think of it as
a mathematical analogy that allows you
to do uh difficult problems easily so
that Fifth Dimension is a spal dimension
yeah yeah that line you got drawn there
that's standing out into the say it
again which line many lines this one
that's in a spatial Dimension yeah these
are space dimensions everything's space
here that would correspond Horizon
located that well this would correspond
to our
Horizon yeah what you're what you're
saying right now though is
experimentally there really not what
they deserve is could also be explained
just sort of the idea you got a b a big
Fireball
of random you know particles being
created by energy thermal energy yeah
well yes the details of it uh you know
the devil is in the details um this
predic about the viscosity was a stunner
nobody expected that so that was purely
the only explanation of that or the only
quantitative explanation of it comes
from the parallel with black
holes
um the that was a stunner that was not
expected there are other interesting
things other interesting kind of
experiments the way particles move
through this plasma um the details of it
may be better described by thinking of
it as a black hole and thinking of it as
uh well thinking of it in terms of
quantum chromodynamics and doing Quantum
chromodynamics correctly and calculating
it honestly if we knew how to do that
should give us the same
answers it's not that this theory is
replacing an older Theory it's believed
to be a mathematically equivalent
description but one that's useful in
contexts where we simp simply can't
calculate Quantum chromodynamics in fact
we've never been able to calculate
Quantum chromodynamics very effectively
except in some very very special
situations no that's
right well in in its five-dimensional
Incarnation it does have gravity and it
does have uh Horizons and its
four-dimensional version this is just a
hot Fireball of quirks and gluons
without gravity
uh what I'm asking but there is
viscosity something right there's the
viscosity can always be described in
principle by understanding hot quirks
and
gluons and but when I say in principle
nobody has known has learned how to do
that Quantum field theory is a difficult
subject nobody knows how to calculate
those sorts of things the equivalence
with gravity gravity of course is also
hard but some things are easy some
things are easy and as it happens
calculating the viscosity of a horizon
is
easy yeah are we going to be able to
figure out why they Collide the beams
instead of running the beam into a still
uh why say it again are we going to be
able to understand why they Collide the
beams instead of running the beams into
a Ste Target oh you no that's easy
that's easy
um is that tonight's lecture what's that
is that a tonight's
lecture well uh I I didn't include it in
tonight's lecture it very well could
have been but let me tell you the answer
if
uh all
right there's something called Center of
mass energy which is the energy of the
system when it's
viewed from the center of Mass frame in
other words when the two particles are
colliding uh with equal an opposite
momentum the center of mass energy is
called
E
naturally okay and
um that's equal roughly
speaking in units in which C is equal to
one it's just equal these are very
relativistic particles relativistic
particles have an energy which is equal
to their momentum and so it's just equal
to twice the
momentum
uh twice the momentum of these particles
in
fact and that can be very large on the
other hand if you
slam the fast particle into a standing
still
particle and you ask what's the center
of mass energy of that in other words
what would be the energy if you went to
the center of mass of this the energy
would be much much
smaller much much smaller it wouldn't be
twice the momentum it would be something
like uh the square root of the mass of
this particle times the momentum of the
fast particle here that's much much
smaller uh the
um this is much smaller than this if the
momentum is large so the point is that
you lose an enormous amount of um
effective energy by letting this
particle stand still if you can
accelerate it to the same speed that the
other one is moving that doesn't give
you twice the energy in effect it gives
you the square of the energy
basically uh so it's it's a much more
energetic Collision to have them Collide
head
on
um we could we will be able to do that
we'll be in a position to do this in
detail but uh not uh not
now but that's the reason energy yeah is
there a reason
why a
cyoc has to be so large is that a
fundamental reason or is it
just well um you know electric and
magnetic fields can only be so big
before uh before they can't be supported
by Steel and uh concrete and the other
things that hold the accelerated
together um you can only create magnetic
fields with which
are you know 10 Tesla or something like
that and it's the magnetic fields that
are accelerating the particles and so
you can't accelerate a particle simply
it's not a matter of in principle it's a
matter of strength of materials all
sorts of engineering things and ability
to create huge magnetic fields that
limit the ability to accelerate
particles over short distances of space
you simply can't create big enough
fields to accelerate a particle to a
relativistic energy a proton to a highly
relativistic energy over a meter uh the
more you want to accelerate it the more
room you need because all the
acceleration is is as it moves along you
give it a push you give it a push you
give it a push you give it a push and so
you got to give it a lot of
pushes and that's all it is I mean
basically the energy of the accelerator
is proportional to its length because it
just accelerates uh with a more or less
uniform energy per uh per meter so they
can't make it where it circulates a few
times but the cyron to be
smaller
um oh well then I think you would simply
run into the I it's not a cyclotron I
think you simply can't create big enough
magnetic fields lasting long enough the
no there's another very important point
the other the other very important Point
has to do with energy loss when you
accelerate a particle a charge by first
of all you can only accelerate charged
particles you can't accelerate neutral
particles now charged particles when
they move in circles
accelerate and the smaller the the
smaller the circle for a given velocity
the bigger the acceleration so a
particle moving in a tight little circle
is highly accelerated acceleration means
radiation and radiation means energy
loss so there's a very very important
technological Point here
that if the circle is too
small it will simply lose energy at
their at a rate which is as big is that
you're dumping the energy in you're
limited in the size of the accelerator
by not wanting it to lose energy by
radiation too fast a straight
accelerator doesn't uh particle moving
in a straight
line with uniform velocity doesn't
accelerate and doesn't
radiate so if you give it a push a push
a push a push well there's a little bit
of acceleration all right which causes
it to radiate but making it turn uh
around in a circle really causes big
problems uh those problems can sometimes
be advantages for example up at slack
they run electrons in circles and they
take off the synchrotron radiation the
radiation that comes off and they use it
for other purposes but if your point is
to get a lot of energy into your charged
particles you want to accelerate them in
as straight a line as possible because
in that way you uh you eliminate the
tendency of the particles to radiate
away their
energy is there a it seems to be that
the straight line and slack is electrons
and these circular ones are pedrons yeah
is there a reason yeah yeah yeah
um electrons are much lighter than uh
are than protons so to get a given
amount of it's energy that's important
you want to dump en
into a small volume and see what comes
out okay now electrons are very much
lighter uh than protons so in principle
you've got to get them up to a larger
velocity for the same
energy uh you've got to get them up to a
larger velocity and in getting them up
to a large of velocity that also means
for a given Circle a larger
acceleration so if you were to
accelerate electrons in the hron
Collider
they would be subject and tried to get
them up to the same energy they would
have a much larger acceleration and a
much larger energy loss so again it's
energy loss the light particle needs to
go faster to have the same energy faster
means more acceleration when it goes in
a circle acceleration means are what
about the other way why why not pyrons
in in the linear
accelerator well
one you could you could do hyrons in the
linear accelerator
[Music]
um why not hyron in the linear
accelerator you you get to you get to
accelerate it many many times as it goes
around in the circle going around in the
circle and accelerating it is equivalent
to having an enormously big accelerator
you get to push it and push it and push
it and push it and push it so yeah you
could do it in the linear accelerator
but you'd have to make the linear
accelerator very very much bigger
you want a good long length to do it in
but you don't want too much radiation
the
hadrons the compromise is to have a big
circle and to keep accelerating along
its route until it's limited by the by
the by the radiation but it'll be
limited by the
radiation at the same velocity that the
electrons would be limited by there all
right same velocity but that means much
more energy for the uh for the
protons
okay let's
uh let's get back to the special theory
of
relativity and um just for fun let's do
one puzzle all problems in special
relativity all puzzles in special
relativity are usually the same they
have to do with one basic flawed concept
that that we uh that we carry around as
evolutionary
baggage and confuses us every time we
have some relativity problem thing to do
is to draw a good
diagram and to remember in detail what
uh what that diagram is telling us
here's the puzzle it's famous
puzzle um it's usually phrased in terms
of a limousine trying to get into a
garage so you have a garage a certain
size
i''s say 12 feet uh 12 feet in length 12
13 feet in length I don't know how long
my garage is probably longer than that
but uh just big enough that an ordinary
car can fit into it and a stretch
limousine once to get into it I don't
know how I'm
not looks like it's going it's going
this
way and the stretch limousine is 20 ft
long once I get into the garage so the
driver says okay I know the special
theory of relativity I'll speed up my
car and whoever's watching from the rest
frame will watch this somebody watching
from the rest frame will watch this and
according to his
calculations my car will be lorence
contracted in the frame of reference of
the garage it'll be lorence contracted
and if I can Loren contracted Enough by
making it move fast enough I can get it
into the garage
getting it into the garage means the
front end and the back end are both
within the garage
simultaneously okay on the other
hand the other view of it is that the
car is standing
still and the garage is moving toward
the car and so from a frame of reference
in which the car is standing still the
garage looks Loren contracted and
therefore is much smaller than the size
of the limo and it's quite clear that
the limo can't get into the garage so we
have a puzzle we have a paradox can the
limousine get in or can't the limousine
get into the garage now as I said what
it means for the limousine to be in the
garage is that the front end and the
back end are simultaneously inside the
garage and the nasty concept that we've
inherited and we have a difficult time
getting rid of is the concept of simult
anity what it means for the two ends of
the car to be
simultaneously inside the garage that's
the rub that simultane simultaneity is
not the same in all reference frames so
the thing to do to understand this
particular problem well first of all we
ought to open the door to the garage to
let the car in so I'm going to open the
door but just for safety
sake I'm also going to open open the
back
door and we'll simply ask can the car is
a car ever simultaneously all of it
inside the garage we won't worry about
what happens if it gets in the garage we
won't worry too much about what happens
when it's decelerated by the back wall
of the garage and the way to avoid that
is we will simply open up the back door
I I don't want to kill a
driver um I would I do wish I had a
better piece of chalk though okay so how
do we analyze this as always the first
thing to do is to draw yourself a
picture Ah that's a good
one draw yourself a picture and get
everything laid out on the
picture vertical axis is time this is
all a problem that takes place in one
dimension one dimension of space so we
don't have to worry very much about Y
and Z pretty much X is all we have to
worry about
uh as the first thing we draw into this
diagram is the light cone the trajectory
of light rays this just orients us it
orients us and um reminds us what very
very fast means the speed of light all
right so we draw in lightlike
trajectories like this okay then we
begin
to
ah then the next thing is to put in our
two Observers one Observer is the
Observer at rest and his coordinates x
and t just look like what's drawn there
the second Observer is moving relative
to the First with a
velocity and so his
axis looks like this this is could be
called T Prime let's put it at a little
bit bigger angle the bigger the angle
the faster he's moving and I want to
exaggerate the
motion so let's put a way out here
moving with something like half the
speed of light or something like
that and we also have to remember that
the xaxis the new xaxis the XP Prime
axis is
tilted relative to the x- axis meaning
that what the new Observer calls
simultaneous is different than what the
old Observer calls simultaneous the old
Observer calls everything on the
horizontal axis simultaneous meaning to
say that it happens at the same time the
new Observer the moving Observer calls
everything
along now it wasn't very well drawn one
more
try I was told when you draw pictures
like this and you want to make straight
lines Take Your Eye Off the chalk and
and only look at the end point but it
never works look at the end point
okay just a
help yeah it's bent over here too much
little
acceler no it's not
acceleration no no it's not this is not
a moving thing this
is yeah
okay yeah they are they
are yes they are are
equal in coordinates in which the speed
of light is
one you don't want to try to draw this
in which in the coordinates in which the
speed of light is
186,000 Miles perss because then this is
practically horizontal and you won't be
able to see
anything all right so in coordinates in
which speed of light is one the picture
looks like this now let's draw in the
garage right first of all there is I
don't know what they call let's call it
the front end this is the front end of
the garage and the back end of the
garage all right the front end of the
garage stands still in our frame of
reference and that means it looks like a
vertical
line the same is true of the back end of
the garage it's also a vertical this end
here it's also a vertical line and it
looks like
this
oops so the region in here between the
two red lines let's just dot it
in maybe I shouldn't let's leave it
white the region between the two red
lines is the interior of the garage now
what about the limousine the limousine
is moving and it's moving with velocity
of the other frame of reference the
other frame of reference is the frame of
reference of the limousine here's the
back end of the limousine the back end
of the limousine over here moves and at
this point let's draw it in green the
back end of the limousine is here the
front end of the limousine is over here
I won't draw it in
yet
uh okay I I will draw in the front end
of the limousine the front end of the
limousine I'm going to put let's see
about over here
there's the front end of the limousine
moving with the same speed of course as
the back
end here it
is now I've opened the back end here the
back door so the limousine goes right
through it doesn't smash into the back
wall it just goes through and our
question is is there any instant of time
at which the entire limousine in other
words the distance from the back green
to the front green or from the the rear
end of the car to the front the portion
of the limousine between the rear end
and the front end is there any time at
which it's all together simultaneously
inside the red now we have to decide
what we mean by
simultaneously if we mean simultaneously
from the point of view of the stationary
Observer that's asking the question is
there any horizontal line that you can
draw here in which both the back end and
the front end
will both appear inside the garage and
yes there are here the back end goes in
over here the front end is still inside
the uh it's right over here the front
end is here's where the front end went
into the garage the front end crossed
the beginning of the garage over here
and the front end went out the rear door
over
here the back end went into the garage
over here and comes out over here
okay so here's a time right over here
when the back end is just getting in and
the front end has not yet gone outside
the garage so yes there is an instant of
time when the entire car is inside the
garage but that's from the perspective
of the stationary
Observer what about the moving Observer
for the moving Observer lines like this
are
simultaneous if I were to take this
point and draw the appropriate line it
would look like
that from the moving observer's point of
view this point and that point are
simultaneous notice that this point and
this point are not both inside the
garage by the time the back end gets in
the front end is
out so from the point of view of the
moving Observer no the H card never was
inside the garage
there's no Paradox there's no
contradiction the contradiction or the
apparent Paradox is simply
by is simply due to not distinguishing
what we mean by
simultaneous in the two frames of
reference that a different
yeah the two green lines and the segment
of the x-axis between the two green
lines and the line that
represents the vehicle being in the
garage you have that forms a
parallelogram
right I mean with this yes yeah sure so
no matter how fast or how slow you go
that black line is the same length as
the vehicle oh yeah well that line is
that line has a length which is the
lorence contracted length of the of the
limousine this is the lorence contracted
length of the
limousine okay it's Loren contracted
length because it's the length of the
limousine as seen from the stationary
reference frame okay if I were to
calculate the proper distance from here
to here that would represent the length
of the limousine in The Limousines
reference frame
yeah
good all right that's a that's a uh
little puzzle that's sort of ill
illustrative of a large number of
puzzles in relativity Theory and usually
the answer is to to remind yourself that
simultaneity is a relative concept and
almost always when you analyze the
experiment in for these kind of puzzles
there's a hidden use of the word
simultaneous and uh and that's where the
uh the Paradox comes
in okay uh now we want to get back to
Lorent transformations to the
mathematics of Lorent
Transformations and uh to some uh we
want to move on
and understand the laws of physics as
they are
described in relativity Theory the same
laws that are for example Newton's Laws
of force Newton's laws of motion and so
forth what happens to them when we move
on to
relativity and we need some mathematics
most of the mathematics is notation not
much more than notation first of all we
have four coordinates X Y and Z and the
fourth coordinate
T it's a convenient notation to lump
them all
together
t x y and
z in fact I usually put T at the
end and call them all by the name
X X1 X2 X3
and x0 y0 instead of four I don't know
that's a standard notation maybe I
should have put the x0 at the beginning
but throughout my notes I seem to have
uh put the x0 at the end of uh at the
end of the
line x0 X1 X2 X3 those correspond to x y
z and T so the odd man out here is X
notot it's the one that is time the
other three are spatial
axes okay Al together we also lump them
all together and call them X mu
mu the Greek letter mu coming from the
rear end of the alphabet represents uh
the uh the indices 1 2 3 and four mu can
go from not 1 2 3 and four 1 2 3 and
zero
x c one yeah we're setting c equal to
one yeah we are setting c equal to one
and when it's interesting to do so I'll
put the C's
back only when it's interesting to do so
for example when we take
non-relativistic limits of situations
and we want to see how things behave for
slowly moving objects in a more
conventional uh situation then it's
convenient to put the C's back in to see
uh to see how we approach the uh
ordinary physics that would be CT or
yeah that would be CT right that would
be
CT yeah
exactly okay exactly now there's
another
symbol which is X with a lower
mu mu in this expression goes
upstairs these are incidentally called
uh let's see these are called
contravariant indices I always forget
out which one is which when they're
upstairs they're called hm
Co is low Co is low and Contra is high
okay physicists call it upstairs and
downstairs we never use that language we
talk about upstairs and downstairs I
will
TR uh okay this again which is it co is
low Co is low okay so these are the
covariant components these are
components of a of an object of a vector
we'll see uh but there are two ways to
describe this is just two dis different
Des descriptions of the same thing and
the difference in the
description is that in the covariant
components of the same Vector you write
them as - x minus y minus Z and
T in other words you take the same
object and you just
consider the space comp
components made
negative if I give you a
point x y
ZT and tell you those are those are the
positions of a certain point and then
ask you what are the covariant indices
of that point what are the covariant
description of that point instead of the
contravariant you just multiply the
space components by minus
one that's its definition you simply
change the sign
of the first three components why do you
do that you do this only for a neat
notation and I'll show you what the neat
notation
is should these be subscripts these are
subscript this is subscript oh it's uh
no no no okay then we could write that
this is
equal this is
X1 this is equal to X1
X2 X3 X not
okay so X1 with a lower index is minus
the X1 of with the upper
index there's nothing there's nothing
fancy going on here you just take the
first three entries and change their
sign and that gives you a new object
which is called x sub
mu right so for example if I pick the
point x = 3 Y = 2 Z = 4 and T =
then the
standard expression here would just be 3
2 4
10 that would be X mu X
mu would equal 3 2 4
10 but
this would be -3 -2 -4 and
10 it's not a different point it's the
same point but it's just a different
notation for the same point same H it's
the same point just a different notation
for it just remember when you see an
object with covariant indices like this
remember if you want to know exactly
where it is in SpaceTime change the sign
of these coordinates here why do you do
this well I'll tell you it makes a nice
it makes a nice
notation it makes a notation which
systematically makes elegant and pretty
equations and helps you keep track of
various minus signs that occur in
relativity okay let's let's consider the
following object summation over mu now
summation over mu means you sum over one
2 3 and zero of X mu X mu what is this
object all right summation over mu
means X1 X1 but what is that what is X1
X1 X1 with a lower index is just the
same as X1 with the upper index except
you change the sign so this is min - X12
which is just -
x^2 what
about X2
X2 X2 X2 this is X2 is y remember that
X2 is
y okay
so in the lower
index representation we change the sign
and this becomes Min -
y^2 and then for Z it's the same thing
minus Z
2 but then plus
t^2 why Plus t^2
because the lower index and the upper
index correspond to exactly the same
sign for the time
component okay so this just reads X1 X1
with a lower index and an upper index
but that's minus X squ Plus X2 lower X2
upper this isn't squared just X2 upper
that's minus y^ 2 next one is minus z^2
and then Plus t^2 but that's exactly the
opposite that's exactly the object that
we called the proper distance from the
origin or the proper time from the
origin to the point xyzt
T so we now have a no notation a
notational trick so far you don't see
what the trick is but you'll find out
that the trick is uh is quite useful
that we can write the proper distance
from the origin to a point in just the
form summation over mu X mux mu with one
index upper and one index
lower
now over and over and over again in
relativity Theory you'll be doing sums
like this where you sum over the first
Direction the second Direction the third
Direction the fourth Direction with the
first three of them having the opposite
sign from the last one that happens over
and over again in fact it happens over
and over so many times that Einstein got
sick of writing the summation sign here
and he just left it
out he said rule whenever you see an
expression like this with an upper index
on a lower index and the upper index and
the lower index are the same it means
some over the indices it's called the
Einstein summation
convention it was probably not
Einstein's most brilliant accomplishment
but it was pretty damn
smart
uh
so X mu X mu this kind of expression
where an index will be
repeated once lower and once upper and
only if it's once upper and once lower
then you you remember to sum over the
index and what do you get you get the
proper distance or the proper time from
the origin to the point xyzt
T so this is a neat notation what is it
for it's a notation for the combination
t^2 - x^2 - y^ 2 - z^ 2 that's all it is
okay is standard symbol for proper time
and Tow is the standard symbol for
proper
time sometimes called s but yes that was
the standard is is a standard symbol for
proper
time
okay all right we'll use that over and
over it gets tiresome to write down x² t
x t^2 - x s - y sare - z^ 2
[Music]
um and so this is the notation that
we'll
use that's one piece of mathematical not
ation I won't call it mathematics it's
just notation that uh that is very very
convenient when studying relativity in
fact it would be very difficult to write
the equations of Relativity without this
uh without this notational
device okay next let's talk about
transformation laws in general in fact
let's talk about not Lorent
Transformations lorence
Transformations are things which mix
time and space together for example if
you consider a uh two um observers which
are moving relative to each other along
the x- axis then we have Loren
Transformations which mix x and t leave
Y and Z alone those are lench
transformations uh and the principle of
Relativity is a principle of symmetry
that says the equations of our Theory
should be symmetric should not change
when we make a loren transformation well
there are other symmetries that are more
familiar
the simplest of which is just rotation
of coordinates in space ordinary spatial
rot coordinate
rotations uh in fact if we combine the
two together Loren Transformations and
spatial
rotations we get a large number of
Transformations which represents
basically the entire set of symmetries
of relativistic physics almost the
entire set but here's the point here's
let's draw in one more
axis here's X here's T and let's draw in
y z is somewhere in the uh in the fourth
dimension we can't see it but it's also
there now I've taught you how to do
Loren Transformations along the x-axis
in other words I've taught you how to
compare the
coordinates of a moving Observer who's
moving along the x axis with the
coordinates of the stationary Observer
right I don't think it would be too hard
oh and remember what it does it mixes x
and t together but leaves y
alone right it leaves y alone it does
not transform the coordinate
perpendicular to the motion to the
relative motion so everybody agrees
about y but they disagree about T and X
but nevertheless they transform into
each other under the luren
Transformations now I think you could
probably figure out if instead of
thinking of two observers moving
relative to each other along the xaxis
suppose we had the second Observer
moving along the Y AIS I think you could
probably figure out how to do the
Transformations instead of writing
things like X Prime is equal to xus VT
over < TK 1 - V ^2 T Prime = uh uh t -
VX over > 1 - V ^2 and Y Prime = Y and
also Z Prime equal
z uh all you would really have to do is
interchange X and Y and write that y
Prime is equal to y - VT T
Prime is T minus v y but X Prime is
equal to
X that wouldn't be very hard you
just realize that what you originally
called the x- axis has now become the Y
AIS and simply make that replace
but supposing you wanted to do a Lorent
transformation in other words you wanted
to consider an observer who is moving
along some funny axis neither X nor y
but along some funny
angle then the thing to do would be
before you make the Loren transformation
do a rotation of coordinates in
space
find a new coordinate X Prime and a new
coordinate y Prime which are just
rotated in space and then do your Loren
transformation along the
new primed
axes by compounding together rotations
of
space with Loren Transformations along
one axis you can construct all of the
possible frames of reference moving
relative to each other with uniform
velocity right if
if they're moving along some not along
one of the original axes all you do is
rotate coordinates from the rotate
spatial coordinates until you have your
axis until you have your axis of motion
aligned with one of the new axes and
then do the lench transformation along
there okay so the other thing then that
we have to know is how to transform
coordinates under rotations of space
now this is something that has nothing
to do with Einstein it goes back
probably to uid I don't know who uh was
the first one who figured out how to
rotate
coordinates I don't know if uid used
coordinates of vectors and I don't think
he did but uh what does that go back to
decart I'm not sure H
deard probably deard
yeah
so um but in any case it goes way way
back past the Einstein just rotations of
coordinates every rotation in space has
an
axis right we can pick our axis let's
pick the z-axis to rotate around if we
pick the z-axis to rotate around then
only X and Y transform all right Z stays
the same so we're rotating about the
z-axis
I don't know where Z is z is vertical
and we're rotating about that axis and
so X and Y get mixed up with each other
let's just write down I'm not going to
prove takes a little bit of trigonometry
to figure out what the uh what the
Transformations
are let's draw the XY plane this way
here's X here's
y here's X Prime here's y
Prime the angle of rotation is Theta
and here's some
Vector with coordinates
XY the question is and coordinates XY
means that if you drop a perpendicular
to the x axis it'll intersect at point x
and if you draw a if you drop a
perpendicular to the Y AIS it will give
you y now you want the primed
coordinates the primed coordinates after
rotation you do the same thing you drop
a perpendicular to the X Prime axis you
drop a perpendicular to the Y Prime axis
and you look at the coordinates in the
XP Prime and Y Prime
axis so that's the
geometry that's the geometry of the
coordinate transformation from X and Y
to X Prime and Y Prime it's just a
matter of dropping perpendiculars to the
appropriate axes all right I'm going to
give you the formula for x Prime and Y
Prime in terms of X and Y it depends on
the angle Theta and you can check this
it's a little bit of
trigonometry Elementary
trigonometry X Prime is equal to x
cosine
Theta + y sin of
theta and Y Prime is equal to - x sin
Theta + y cosine
Theta you can check that for example
when Theta is 0 degrees what does it say
when Theta is 0 degrees s of theta is 0o
cosine of theta is 1 so it says X Prime
is equal to X and it says y Prime is
equal to y That's good a rotation by 0
degrees is no rotation at all now try a
rotation by 90° and you'll see that it
also works and that's the general
rotation of coordinates
now this transformation there's
something which is left invariant by
this transformation it's the distance to
the point
XY by left invariant I mean that the
distance the square of the distance to
the point XY what is that the square of
the distance is X2 +
y^2 uh if you move the pl if you move
the point out of the plane you might
also add in z^2 oh let's let's add let's
add in z z Prime is equal to
Z you're rotating about the z-axis and
so nothing happens to
Z all right what this transformation
leaves invariant is X2 + y^2 + z^2 let's
only do let's just do let's start with x
squ + y^2 let's forget Z for the
moment that means that after you've made
the
transformation x^2 + y^2 is the same
thing as X Prime 2 + y Prime 2
well geometrically the reason is because
it doesn't matter whether you calculate
the distance by referring to the
original coordinates or the rotated
coordinates the distance must be the
same distance is what you measure with a
tape measure and the tape measure uh
doesn't know what your way your
coordinates are so the answer has to be
the same x^2 + y^2 must be equal to X
Prime s + y Prime squ but you can check
that you can check that for example X
Prime Prim squ is let me just call
cosine Theta C and sin Theta s so I
don't have to write so much X Prime squ
what's X Prime s that's x^2 c^
2 + y^2
s² plus T
XY
CS X2 c^ 2 + y^ 2 S 2 + twice the cross
term that's X Prime squ
what about y Prime
squ that's y Prime squ is
X2 s
s from here plus y^2 c^
2 from the second term and then minus
because there's a minus sign here minus
2xy
CS now add them
together all right on the left hand side
you just get X Prime 2 + y Prime
2 but on the right hand side you get
x2 * cosine squ + sin s cosine s + sin s
is 1 right so that's just
X2 y^2 you also have S S2 + c^ 2 so
that's just
y^2 and the cross term here just cancels
2xy Cs and minus 2xy CS this goes away
all right so we're only proving what's
obvious anyway that the expression for
the distance doesn't depend exactly on
how you Orient the axes it's always just
x^2 + y^2 if we add it in Z Prime equals
z since Z is equal the same as Z Prime
we could also
say that the distance in three
dimensions is unchanged Z is the same as
Z Prime so there's nothing new
there the
rotations mathematically are
transformations on the components which
preserve the length which keep the
length
unchanged that's the mathematical
definition of the
rotations all right now there's another
way to write such a transformation I
wonder people seem to be walking in they
seem to be a little bit confused
is this 200 or is this
2011 21 okay
yeah yeah okay
so that's the idea of rotations if you
combine the rotations with Lorent
transformations in other words after
having made the transformation to X
Prime and Y
Prime and also T Prime is equal to T
if you like if you want to think about
the full four
dimensions uh then you can go and do a
new Loren transformation along the x-
Prime T Prime axis and in that way build
an observer who is moving along the new
XP Prime axis rather than the old x
axis so combining rotations and Loren
Transformations basically gives you a
wide class of different Transformations
which correspond to the rotations of all
kinds and Lorent Transformations along
all the possible
axes uh that you could uh that you could
do them
along all right now more notation more
notation notation is boring but once you
get it you've got it and uh it makes
equations much easier simpler and uh
easy to
manipulate everybody here know a little
bit of linear
algebra that's the wrong question does
anybody here not know a little bit of
linear
algebra everybody knows linear algebra
good we don't need to we don't need to
uh okay good that's excellent all right
now there are two ways that we could
write this these these equations like
this let's just take this one here we
could write it in a matrix form X Prime
y Prime is equal to some Matrix time
XY The Matrix would in fact just be
cosine Theta sin Theta minus sin Theta
cosine
Theta we could also write it in another
form we could write X and we could also
put here we also put here Z Prime Z
Prime
Z and then the Matrix would
be a 3X3 Matrix 0
01 The Matrix would then act among the
XY components here to mix them up
leaving Z out of the picture all
together and then it would act on Z to
give Z Prime which would just be Z equal
Z Prime so every such transformation has
a matrix associated with it
um and there's another way to write this
we could also write this in another form
x i
Prime now I is only going from 1 to
three so far I haven't mixed in time x
Prime I I could be 1 2 or 3 representing
X Y or Z is equal to m i
j
XJ where MJ just represent the
components of the Matrix this is the
same
expression uh multiply and and summing
over J as always when we see repeated
index we sum over J in this case since
it's only got to do with space in no
time no different well I'm not going to
worry about upstairs and downstairs
indices it's only when time comes into
it that we worry about
that uh this is a way of writing a
vector is equal to a matrix times a
vector and we can write it this way here
both exactly the same
expression okay any question about that
because if you know if you know this
then we can move on to Lorent
Transformations Lorent
Transformations also have a similar form
they're also matrices multiplied by
components
so let's work let's work that out in
detail let's work out the Matrix
Associated this is the Matrix associated
with a certain rotation this isn't the
most General rotation this is the most
General rotation about the z-axis we
could rotate about some other axis and
it gets more complicated but uh this is
typical of a rotation
Matrix good let's write a len
transformation X Prime is = to x - VT
over < TK 1 - V ^
2 y Prime is equal is equal to
y z Prime is equal to Z and T Prime is
equal to t -
VX / < TK of 1 - V ^2 this is just a
good old lorence transformation except
with Y and Z doing nothing staying the
same okay we can also write this in
terms of a 4x4
Matrix the 4x4
Matrix
equation here's our
Matrix okay X let's put let's label the
entries x
y z t or X1 X2 X3 x x
not x y z
t let's see what our entries are the
coefficient in X Prime the coefficient
multiplying X is 1 /are < TK of 1 - V ^2
the coefficient multiplying Y is 0
0 and uh
minus
V over < TK of 1 minus v^
2 let's see 0 I'll one 0
0 0 0 1 0
and - V over < TK 1 - v^ 2 0
0 V over 1 minus v^2 okay let's let's
see what this does
I
maintain that if I take the column
Vector X Prime y Prime Z Prime T
Prime and I set it
equal to this Matrix times the column
xyzt
T that that really is a loren
transformation let's see what does it
say it says that X Prime is equal to
let's forget
this it says that X Prime
is equal do I have it wrong uh no I have
[Music]
it yeah the fourth one here is
one okay yeah all right so this says
that X Prime is equal to x / < TK 1 - V
^ 2us VT over > 1 - v^ 2 with nothing
mixing in from Y and Z that's correct it
also says that y Prime is equal to y y z
Prime is equal to Z and T Prime is minus
v/ 1 - V ^ 2 *
X Plus 1 / > 1 - V ^2 T that's the other
that's the last equation here so once
again a lorence transformation can be
written as a matrix multiplying the
column xyzt t a rotation can be written
as a as a matrix
multiplying the column XYZ T we don't
usually think of the rotations as having
to do anything with t but we just think
of a
rotation as a spatial rotation but that
just means that t Prime is equal to T
when we do a rotation so we have 4x4
matrices which correspond to rotations
we can call them R and we have 4x4
matrices which correspond to Loren
Transformations we can call them l
what if we want to do a transformation a
loren transformation along some other
axis what we do is we first use the
rotation
Matrix to rotate axes and then we use
the Loren transformation matrix to boost
or to give us some velocity along the
new X Prime axis in other words what it
comes down to is you multiply rotation
matrices by lorence matrices you first
rotate you first rotate and then you
Loren
transform you multiply the matrices
together to find what the action would
be for a loren transformation along some
other
angle let me work out one
useful application of matrix
multiplication not ing rotations into
the game
now we're not going to do much with
rotations of space and Loren
transformation
simultaneously it's enough to know that
our laws of physics are invariant under
rotations and luren Transformations
along one single axis because if they're
invariant under rotations and Loren
Transformations along an axis then they
will be invariant under the Lorent
transformation along any axis so
uh symmetry under rotation well that's
easy we all know how to think about that
it's symmetry on the Lorent
Transformations that we're interested
in what I want to work out using matrix
multiplication is the compounding of
velocities if I am moving relative to
you with velocity V and there's a third
Observer who is moving moving relative
to me with velocity
you okay the that's me relative to you
you that's him relative to me got that V
Rel wow V me relative to you you him
relative to me is that
clear I think you got it all right then
what's the transformation between him
and you okay what's the velocity that
you will see him move with relative to
you get me out of the picture eliminate
me okay that velocity will called W but
the trick is to find W in terms of v and
U now in old-fashioned pre-risc physics
the answer was his velocity is V plus u
I'm moving with velocity v he's moving
relative to me with velocity U the
natural expectation in ordinary
Newtonian physics would be that him
relative to U is velocity V plus u so
this is the formula for pre-
relativistic physics pre- Einstein
physics W is equal to V plus
u it can't be the right
thing we know that in relativity Theory
it's impossible to exceed the speed of
light and if I can move with 3/4 of the
speed of light relative to
you and he can move with 3/4 of the
speed of light relative to me if we use
this formula he is going to be moving
relative to U with one and a half times
the speed of light so something's wrong
this can't be right to figure it out
correctly all we need to do is to
compound two Loren Transformations one
with velocity V and one with velocity U
and that corresponds to matrix
multiplication let's just we don't need
Y and Z in
here let's write down the Matrix for the
transformation between you and me okay
that's just one over let's see what is
it it's 1 over Square < TK 1 - V ^ 2 V
overare < TK 1 - V ^ 2 V over Square <
TK
minus uh minus V over 1 - v^ 2 1 over 1
- v^2 I just threw away
the
uh everything but the XT part of this
transformation that's the
Matrix
that takes us let us say from your
coordinates to my
coordinates now there's a second
transformation which takes from my coord
coordinates to his coordinates and that
transformation has the
form um let's call it xou Prime and T
Prime that's his coordinates and that's
equal to 1 over 1 - u^ 2 sare <
TK - U overare < TK of 1 - u^
uunk 1 - u^ 2us s and then 1 / < TK 1 -
U
^2 that's the
transformation
times x Prime T
Prime so this takes us from me to him
and this takes us from you to me what is
the transformation which takes you to
him all we have to do is plug in for X
Prime here this Matrix time XT and so we
see that X Prime P
Prime is equal
we have to multiply these two matrices
together to find the transformation
between you and him okay this is not so
hard to do let's uh let's actually
multiply the
Transformations Let's Do It Let's uh
spend uh 5 minutes doing
it let's see we have this times this
minus this times this that's going to be
one plus UV I think in the in the corner
over here 1 plus UV if I'm not mistaken
does that look
right 1 * 1us
[Music]
- plus u * V yeah right what about the
next Corner over here that's 1 * - V and
minus
U say it
again I think it's minus V minus U is
that right
I think it's also minus V minus U down
here and I think it's 1 plus UV over
here okay now the question is does this
have the
form what what form do we want it to
have let's
see 1/ 1 - w^2 sare < TK
W over < TK of 1 -
w^2 - W over the < TK of 1 - w^2 1
over in other words does it actually
itself have the form of a Lorent
transformation and if so what is the
W okay the answer is yes it does have
the form of a Laurence transformation
but I'm not going to work the whole I'm
not going to prove that this whole make
here has this form what I'm going to do
instead is just show you how to pick off
the value of
w the value of w is easy to pick off you
know what it is it's just the
ratio of this to
this the value of w If This truly has
the form of a loren transformation then
it's easy to pick off the the value of w
it's just the ratio of the component
over here to the component over here
with a minus sign right minus the ratio
of this to this is just
W so if all I want to do is pick off the
velocity of the compound transformation
and not bother trying to prove that it
actually has this form which it does all
we have to do is look at the ratio of
this component to this component and
that must be
W so we can read it off w
is equal to U +
V ided 1 +
UV that's it that's all we have to do to
figure out what the relative velocity
between you and him is compound the
transformation go back later and prove
that this really has this
form uh but if all we want to do is
figure out the velocity of him relative
to U or to to U all we have to do is
work out what the
ratio of this component to this
component is minus V minus or or v+ U /
1+ UV that's the velocity W now uh we
could put some
um we could put some speeds of light
into
this
the units of u and v of velocity and the
units of w are also supposed to be
velocity so that looks pretty good the
only thing wrong with it is you can't
add UV which has velocity squared to one
unless you first divide it by the speed
of light
squared so including the speed of light
W is equal to u+ V that's what Newton
would have said he would have said just
U plus
v but Einstein comes in and throws this
thing into the denominator here okay
throws this thing into the KN if both
youu and V are positive imagine you and
V are positive we're all I'm going down
the veloc the x-axis with positive
velocity he's going down relative to me
with the Positive
velocity then 1 plus UV is bigger than
one and W will be less than u+
V in fact this formula will never get
bigger than the speed of light in fact
let's see what it does do if uh
Let's uh take a crazy limmit let's see
let's take a crazy limit in which u and
v are both very close to the speed of
light okay they're very very close to
the speed of light essentially equal to
the speed of light then what does w come
out to be well the top becomes just
twice the speed of
light and the bottom that's bad twice
the speed of light but the bottom u and
v are both equal to the speed of light
so UV over c^2 is 1 1 1 + 1 is
2 it hasn't gotten bigger than the speed
of
light okay even if you're compounding
two velocities Each of which is
exceedingly close to the speed of light
so close that I can say it is the speed
of light I add them up I get something
which is no bigger than the speed of
light in fact which is just the speed of
light uh it's not hard to prove that
this expression never gets bigger than
the speed of light as long as u and v
are not bigger than the speed of light
as long as u and v are not bigger than
the speed of light the composite here
the composite velocity cannot be and
that's easy to
prove
uh but it's more or less clear since
I've gone to the absolute limit where u
and v are as big as possible and I still
haven't gotten bigger than the speed of
light it's pretty clear that I can't
exceed the speed of light by compounding
any
number uh of Lorent Transformations the
result will always come out less than
the speed of light so this is an
exercise in matrix
multiplication
uh
which is the neat tool for this
particular kind of
operation all right I next want to come
to the concept of velocity in relativity
before we even talk about velocity let's
talk about four
vectors it's
evident that the coordinates of a point
can be thought of as the components of
vectors x y and z are the components of
a displacement Vector from the origin
but XYZ and T can be thought of is the
components of a four-dimensional
vector including
time whose components are these objects
X
mu X mu are the components of a for VOR
a four Vector is one which includes not
just three spatial components but a Time
component
also we can have more General object
just as we can have all kinds of vectors
in space velocity vectors acceleration
vectors uh electric field vectors all
kinds of vectors not only XM itself we
can have a general concept of a vector v
mu a vector is a thing which
transforms under Lorent Transformations
and rotations the same way that XM
transforms it has four
components and if you want to know how
its value in any coordinate system you
simply transform it from coordinate
system to coordinate system using the
same lorence transformation that you
coordinate transform x
with I won't bother writing that down
but if you write down the Len
transformation for x's and simply
substitute
in the uh instead of x's V's that is the
way for vectors
transform there are other four vectors
oh before we talk about how four vectors
trans
form this is
some let's also talk about the
contravariant no covariant this is the
contravariant form of the vector and
consists of four V1 V2 V3
V4 there is also the covariant form for
the vector which is just a notational
device exactly the same things V4
except the three space components have
minus
signs you simply change the sign of the
space
component and that's equal to
V1 V2
V3 V KN not four
not not four
not sometimes I'll write four instead of
not
um
the just as there's a concept of proper
distance of a vector X there's the
concept of the proper length of any
vector
v and that is just given by V mu V
mu is the length of V Square
we can just call it v^
2 it's analogous to X mu X
mu is equal to t^ sared where to would
be the proper distance from one end to
the other end of the vector here it's
just a general notation representing A
New Concept It's A New Concept you can't
ask me why this is the definition this
is the definition of the length of a
four Vector what does it mean it means V
squ - V1 2 - v2^ 2 - V3 2 exactly like
ordinary vectors except with this extra
minus sign v^ 2 minus V1 2us V2 2us V3 2
is called the proper length of a vector
v and it can be written in this form
with a lower index and an upper index
implicitly summed
over that's a useful in fact you can
even go a little bit further you can say
supposing you have two vectors
V and uh and
W then you can invent the product of the
two
vectors and think of that as analogous
to the dotproduct of two vectors I don't
know what to call it this is this is
what it's called W mu V mu but you can
think of it as being analogous to the
dotproduct of two vectors in ordinary
space w * V it represents a kind of
product of the two vectors and the
important point is that this quantity is
invariant if you change frames of
reference that changes the components of
both W and V but it does not change W mu
V mu so quantities like that are
invariant they don't change under Lorent
Transformations and they don't they
don't depend on what family of
coordinate axes you
use okay that's uh that's the idea of a
four Vector but let me come to a
particular four Vector the particular
four Vector is the velocity 4 Vector of
a
particle obviously we want to talk about
things like velocity and
acceleration in Newtonian physics
velocity is a
vector but it's a three Vector three
components it doesn't have a fourth
component in relativity Theory anything
that has three components will have a
fourth component
component and uh velocity is a quantity
which has four components what are those
four components well let's start with
the space components of
velocity here's what I usually mean by
velocity dxdt that's the X component of
velocity let's call that
VT and there
dydt sorry this is V sorry VX X this is
VY and likewise for
VZ okay this is the ordinary concept of
velocity the time rate of change of the
position of a
particle but what would be the time
component of the Velocity
dtdt that's just
one that doesn't make
sense we have an object which really
doesn't have four components one of the
components here is just completely
trivial this can't be what uh a good
relativist would think of as the
velocity so let me explain to you the
way relativity Theory views the velocity
of a
particle I mean this is a perfectly good
definition of velocity it's just not a
thing which transforms nicely under
Loren Transformations it doesn't have a
nice uh uh way of transforming when you
transform the
coordinates here's the definition of
velocity that turns out to be more
useful you start with your coordinates
we're working in with particular
coordinates x and t and y and z t
x every point of SpaceTime is labeled
with a set of coordinates x and t x XYZ
and T right now a particle moves through
here and along the trajectory along the
world line of the particle it could also
be moving in Y and Z it could be moving
out of the Blackboard but along the
trajectory of the particle the little
displacement is called DX DX
mu DX mu can represent the displacement
along the x- axis the Y axis but it can
also represent the displacement along
the time axis so DX knot represents the
displacement along the time axis the X
represents the displacement along the x-
axis and the Y and the Z similarly
represent the little displacements right
so we have four of them from here to
here there are four little differential
distances along the world line of the
particle okay now ordinary
I would divide these by DT but DT is the
time as seen in a stationary reference
frame instead I'm going to divide it by
the DT in the frame of reference of the
moving particle so as as the moving
particle moves along it has a watch and
it takes off time and it asks how much
has my X displacement how much have I
moved in X in a given amount of proper
time how much have I moved in y in a
given amount of proper time how much
have I moved in Z in a given amount of
proper time now proper time is invariant
it doesn't change from coordinate frame
to coordinate
frame so if we divide DX mu by D to
where D to is the proper time from here
to
here that is a four Vector which will
trans transform the same way as X does X
mu or little differences in XM transform
with Loren Transformations conventional
Loren Transformations dividing by DT
doesn't change that because DT doesn't
change under a loren transformation so D
xdt becomes a four Vector it's got four
components and let's see if we can see
what those four components are in terms
of the old-fashioned velocity
the oldfashioned velocity VX VY and VT
sorry VX VY and VZ was VZ the
zdt let's see if we can relate these
things to the oldfashioned kind of
velocities in incidentally this is
called U super
mu it's called the proper
velocity by proper here it means the
time that's being used to differentiate
with is the proper
time okay all right let's see if we can
figure out what it is let's write let's
just take let's take for example DX by
DT that's equal to DX by
DT time DT by
DT likewise for y Dy by DTA is dy by DT
time DT by D
to and so forth
in fact we can even write down that DT
by D sorry yes DT by DT that's the
fourth component of the Velocity Vector
DT by that's just DT by
DT so if I knew what DT by DT
was I would know how to go back and
forth between oldfashioned kind of
velocity dxdt and this new kind of
relativistic velocity
U okay let's figure out what DT by DT is
it's not very
difficult first of all let's write that
d to^ 2 is equal to dt^ 2 minus dx^ 2
minus d y s minus dc^
2 that's just the definition of a small
proper time interval
here it has a DX it has a Dy it has a DZ
and it has a d T and the proper length
of that little Vector is dt^ 2 - dx^ 2 -
d y^ 2 - d c^ 2 okay now let's divide
this by dt^ 2
well this is just
one minus now what is this this is V sub
this is dxdt sared that's VX
s this is vy^
2 and this is minus vz^
2 but what's VX s + v y sare + VC s
that's just the magnitude of the
velocity of the particle and that's the
magnitude of the of the ordinary
velocity it's the magnitude of the
ordinary velocity and so this is just 1
minus V ^ 2 where this V here represents
the full velocity of the particle that's
equal to DT by dt^ 2 or better yet d by
DT is equal to the square < TK of 1us
v^2 that's great because I now know what
DT by DT is it's just one over
this so DT by D
to is equal to 1 / < TK of 1 - V
^2 that tells
us that let's write the let's write down
the equations
now
uux is equal to DX by DT that's
VX time d t by D to that's < TK of 1 - V
^2 likewise with uy and u
z v y / < TK of 1us V ^2 and u z is
equal to v z over < TK of 1us V ^2 what
about the fourth
component the fourth component is just
DT by
DT DT by DT d x by DT d y by DT DT by DT
and finally D DT by DT that is just
U which is equal to 1 / < TK of 1 -
v^2 so here are the four components of
the velocity of the relativistic
Velocity Vector in terms of the ordinary
velocities okay notice that if the
velocity this really should be as always
a c squ down here
V ^2 over
c^2 and notice that if the velocity is
small by comparison with the speed of
light then the thing in the denominator
is just one ux is the same as VX u y is
the same as VY u z is the same as VZ as
long as the velocity is small by the by
the comparison with the speed of light
and U Zer is just one just one DT by DT
that's if the velocity is slow but when
the velocity gets fast there's
appreciable differences between u and
v in fact U is typically let's see 1
minus v^ s so this is bigger than one
yeah U is typically less than V is that
right no U is typically bigger than V
yeah U is bigger than
v u is typically bigger than v i take
uh 1 - v s y U is bigger than
V and in particular u0o is nowhere as
near one it gets
huge okay this is the concept of the
relativistic four Vector of velocity of
a moving
particle it's a four
Vector it transforms if you know it in
one frame of reference you can compute
it in any other frame of reference just
by transforming it this same way as Xyz
and T
transform and uh that makes it much
easier to work with than the ordinary
velocity which has a very complicated
transformation
property
now I'm going to stop soon but let me
just tell you another way of thinking
about this this uh four Vector of
velocity
it has an analog in ordinary ukian
geometry anybody know what it
is it's the tangent Vector to a curve if
you have a world
line
then this notion of four velocity is
basically here it is is basically the
tangent Vector to the trajectory along
the trajectory but let me show you about
tangent vectors in ordinary geometry not
relativistic
geometry imagine you have some curve in
space two-dimensional space
three-dimensional space it doesn't
matter much and I want to construct the
components of the tangent Vector the
tangent Vector means a
vector along the curve of unit
length a vector a unit Vector which is
tangent to the curve at this point here
well the little differential
displacement here
DX now I'm talking only about ordinary
space is obviously pointing along the
tangent Vector it's just this little
Vector over here from here to here DX it
points along the tangent Vector but it's
not a unit Vector it's a very small
Vector what do we want to do to make a
unit vector and I'll tell you what we
want to do we divide the X
by the
distance along the curve in other words
we take this little differential
displacement that gives us DX Dy and
DZ and we divide it by the distance
along there what is the distance along
there it's D
S2 is equal to dx2 + D y^2 + dz^2
and we simply Define the tangent vector
to be DX by
DS DX Dy by
DS and DZ by
DS this is for ordinary geometry no time
just ordinary space we Define the
tangent Vector incidentally can you see
why this tangent Vector is a unit
Vector it's because the sums of the
squares of each component are equal to
one why is that because d s^ s is dx2 +
the Y plus dz^2
right so if I square up the
components and add them
together D X2 + d y^ s + dz^2 is the s s
and so this is a unit
vector and it's just gotten by taking
the little differential displacement
along the curve and dividing it by the
small distance along that differential
displacement and then letting it uh you
know shrink to zero ordinary calculus
this is the same idea here instead of
dividing by the ordinary distance you
divide by the proper time between the
points little DX and you divide by the
proper time so this is the analog this
is the relativistic analog of the
tangent Vector along the uh along the
world line of a
particle as I said it's space SP
components if the particle is moving
slow its space components are the
ordinary velocity and its time
coordinate is just one if a particle is
moving fast then these are appreciably
different than uh than their
non-relativistic uh
analogs yeah
C say it again
uh well um proper time is usually
something measured along a Tim like
trajectory
uh if C is equal to
one apart from the funny minus sign
that's appeared
yes um you can't by taking c equal to
one you can't get rid of a minus sign in
a
formula so I'm not sure what you mean by
saying is proper time the same as proper
distance oh oh I'm sorry you mean
in
uh here I was simply talking about
ordinary ukian geometry distance is
distance there's no question of proper
time because time doesn't even come into
it okay proper distance and I've called
that
s okay in relativity the analog along
here along a trajectory is detau and I
would call it proper time here I would
just call it distance here I would call
it proper
time you could call it proper distance
if you like but uh it doesn't add very
much it's just a distance measured by a
tape measure along the
curve right here it's also just distance
but distance measured by a clock along
the
curve
yeah so it's basically the same concept
the tangent Vector the velocity Vector
now of course you can differentiate the
velocity Vector with respect to proper
time along the curve and that gives you
the proper acceleration vector why would
we be interested in the proper
acceleration
vector because the analog of Newton's
equations fals ma becomes a statement
about proper acceleration but proper
acceleration is not the second
derivative of x with respect to T but
the second derivative of x with respect
to distance or or with respect to proper
time along the curve so if we want to
understand how Newton's equations change
we want to understand proper velocity
proper acceleration another
example let's see I think we could
should I stop here or should I go
another five another 10
minutes all right we'll go another 10
minutes and just illustrate the concept
of
momentum momentum is an important
Concept in mechanics we haven't gotten
to mechanics yet but as you might might
imagine we will have a relativistic
concept of
momentum momentum is a
vector in ordinary
physics in relativistic physics it's
part of a four
Vector okay so let's go through that in
ordinary Newtonian mechanics
MV is equal to the momentum P we could
put some indices on here the X component
of velocity y component of velocity or
we could just put a little Vector index
here to tell us that we're talking about
vectors so momentum and velocity are
vectors mass is just a
number incidentally in the modern
terminology one doesn't speak about Mass
changing with velocity mass is simply a
characteristic of a
particle that uh it's what used to be
called rest Mass when one speaks of mass
it's a number that's attached to the
particle it is what used to be called
Mass when the particle is at rest and
we'll see what it's connected to but uh
just think of mass as something
associated with a particle and not with
its
velocity so if you look up the mass of
an electron in a table of masses of
particles it won't tell you the mass as
a function of velocity it will just tell
you the mass of an electron is blah blah
blah blah blah
kilograms and uh it doesn't change with
velocity it's simply the number that's
uh that's attached to the
electron okay the analog
of
momentum in fact the momentum of a
particle in relativistic theory is not
gotten by multiplying the mass by the
ordinary velocity but rather the mass by
the relativistic
velocity so the right definition in
relativity theory is that mu with four
components is equal to the
mass time U
mu that's four
components momentum in non-relativistic
physics only had three components but
it's interesting to ask what the fourth
component is I'll tell you next time how
you use the momentum you use the
momentum because it's
conserved if you want to know what
happens to particles when they Collide
or partic when they Decay and so forth
the basic tool is conservation of
momentum but not conservation of three
components of momentum but conservation
of all four
components uh so we ought to find out
what the fourth component the momentum
is what about the first three
components PX let's say that's M * ux
which is M * VX / < TK 1 - V ^2 over c^2
okay if V is
small 1 - v^2 over c^2 is basically just
one and so for small velocity the
momentum is just MV right as the
velocity gets bigger and bigger the
momentum the momentum starts changing
and deviating away from just MV in fact
it gets bigger than just MV but for
small velocities it's just a good old
momentum what about the time component
this is something new or is it what
about the time component or equivalently
p
z what is it all right it's energy
energy is also conserved and the fourth
component of the momentum Vector is
energy let's see if we can see why
that's
true first of all it's
[Music]
m ID the square root of 1 - V ^2 and
let's put in the speeds of light
now now I lied to you a little bit I
said that PT is energy it's not quite
true you have to multiply it by the
speed of speed of light squared to get
energy the main point is that it's
conserved whether or not you multiply it
by the speed of light squared is a
matter of convention and a matter of
making it consistent with older choices
of units
energy has certain units what are the
what is the energy what are the what are
the units of energy the units of energy
are masstimes Velocity
squared where did I get that from 1 12
mv^ squ is the kinetic energy of a
particle in ordinary uh in ordinary
relativistic physics so if PT has
anything to do with energy then you
better multiply it by c^ SED in order to
have units of energy but apart from
units it's just PT apart from putting in
the appropriate powers of C to give it
the units that we're familiar with when
we talk about energy PT is the energy
let's see let's go a little bit further
let's work this out and see that it's
energy see that it uh that it's related
to non-relativistic energy kinetic
energy all right first of all this is
mc^
stimes 1 - v^ 2 / c^ 2 to the- one2
power
because it's in the denominator it's to
a negative power and because it's a
square root it's the power a
half okay now I want to work this out
for small velocities for velocities very
much smaller than the speed of light to
do that we use the binomial
theorem the binomial theorem
says the main thing for our purposes is
that the binomial theorem says is that 1
minus a small number let's call it
Epsilon to any power
p is approximately equal to 1 minus P
Epsilon that's the binomial theorem you
can for
example there are higher orders in
epsilon plus things of order Epsilon
squar Epsilon Cub whatever higher orders
an Epsilon but for example 1 - Epsilon
2ar is 1 - 2 Epsilon plus Epsilon 2
Epsilon squ is very very small we're not
interested in it what about 1us Epsilon
[Music]
cubed that's 1 - 3 Epsilon plus things
which are order Epsilon squar if Epsilon
squ is very small then 1 - Epsilon to a
power is just 1us the power 1 - p *
Epsilon you uh that's that's what the
binomial theorem tells us about General
powers of 1 minus Epsilon all right
now v^2 over c^2 is small for a slowly
moving particle v^2 over c^ s is truly
very small for ordinary velocities and
so I can apply this Rule and it says
that this is mc^
2 * 1
now we have a minus from here but we
have another minus from here and it
comes out to be
plus 12 v^2 over
c^2 plus additional things which are
very very much smaller than v^2 over c^
s the next one will be order V4 over C
to the 4th that's impossibly small for
any ordinary velocity and so this is
basically a good approximation for
slowly moving objects mc^ 2 * 1 + 12 D
^2 over c^2 and now the rest is familiar
It's mc^
s that's uh you've seen that before but
that's only the energy if the object is
at rest if it's moving there's another
term which is 12 M the C SES cancel
v^2 this is the ordinary Newtonian
kinetic energy of a moving particle and
you add that to the constant mc^ s
that's what the fourth component of
momentum is or at least for slowly
moving non-relativistic
particles the fourth component of
momentum is a
constant which is characteristic of the
particle mc^
S
Plus the ordinary Newtonian kinetic
energy
adding in a constant to the energy of a
particle if a particle is not allowed to
change its mass and in Newtonian physics
particles never change their
Mass uh if a particle cannot change its
mass and you have any number of
particles then all of this adds up to
some constant and an additional constant
in the energy doesn't make any
difference so the important term in the
energy when particles are moving slowly
is this one and half m v ^ 2 that's the
term in the energy which depends on the
velocity it's what we call kinetic
energy so that's uh that's the four
Vector of momentum includes momentum and
energy the conservation of the four
Vector of momentum is the conservation
of momentum and energy they go together
okay even more when you Lorent transform
from one frame to another momentum and
energy get mixed up with each other
because they're components of a four
Vector
so what
is energy in one frame becomes a
combination of energy and momentum in
another frame but in every frame the
momentum is conserved that's the
important thing momentum is conserved in
every reference frame which means all
four components energy and momentum of
an isolated system are the same before
and after a Collision we'll work out
some examples and use it next time and
then I want to go on to Newton's
equations the concept of
acceleration but then wave equations
wave equations because we're going to
want to study electricity and magnetism
we're going to study light want to study
light light waves and so forth and so we
want to understand
how waves fit into relativity and how
particle motion fits into relativity
particle motion what's the analog of f
equals ma okay that be next time any
questions
now we had a long night tonight didn't
[Music]
we the proceeding program is copyrighted
by Stanford University please visit us
at stanford.edu